TRIGA reactor records 6948211
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
TRIGA reactor records
1967-1981
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Columbia University
6948211
UA#0284
2 linear feet 2 record cartons
The collection consists of the TRIGA reactor records from 1967 to 1972 as well as correspondence with the US Atomic Energy Commission from 1978 to 1981.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least three business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Restrictions on Access
All administrative records of the University are restricted for 25 years from the date of creation.
Accruals
No additions are expected.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series: Series I: TRIGA reactor records, 1967-1981.
Biographical / Historical
As part of the Nuclear Science and Engineering program, a nuclear reactor was built for education and research purposes in the Engineering Terrace building. The application for construction was accepted by the Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) in 1963 and the building project was completed in April 1967 at a total cost of approximately one million dollars. However, the reactor was never fueled and was never radioactive. When Columbia applied to the AEC for an operating license, they received numerous petitions for intervention from residents and activists. Due to the prevailing climate at that time (student unrest and community opposition), Columbia asked AEC to place a hold on the application for the operating license. Columbia reapplied in summer 1969 but the application was denied by the Atomic Safety and Licensing Board (ASLB) because of conflicting estimates of the amount of radioactive material that would be released in a postulated accident. In 1971 an Appeal Board overturned the original ASLB decision and recommended issuance of a license to Columbia. In 1972 interveners filed a petition in the U.S. Court of Appeals for a review of the decision, which the Court later denied. The interveners then petitioned the Supreme Court for review of the Appeal Board decision. By 1974 Columbia was in the process of re-evaluating the Nuclear Science and Engineering program and the need for the nuclear reactor. With changes in upper management and financial considerations, the project was put on indefinite hold. The related instruments were donated to other institutions.
Related Materials
Additional materials related to the TRIGA reactor at Columbia can be found in Central Files (UA#0001) (find under Triga Research Reactor, Triga Atomic Reactor and/or Triga Reactor and Classified research file, Box 635) and in Historical subject files (UA#0002).
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence, proposals, testimony, reports, legal decisions, press releases, product descriptions, petitions, and other materials relating to the TRIGA nuclear reactor that was to have been installed in Engineering Terrace in the late 1960s to early 1970s as a "teaching reactor" for use and study by students.
Correspondence includes that between the University's counsel and its president, between and among physics and other faculty, University administrators, including Robert K. Novick, Director of the Columbia Radiation Laboratory; the Atomic Energy Commission, and General Dynamics. Correspondence and testimony for and against the reactor's presence on the Morningside campus is scattered throughout the files.
Nuclear energy -- Research; Nuclear energy -- New York (State); Columbia University; Columbia University. School of Engineering
- Series I: TRIGA reactor records, 1967-1981
  - Correspondence
    - 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1971-1972, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - Binder, including summary of TRIGA reactor project, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Annual Report to Congress of the Atomic Energy Commission, 1970 (Box 2)
  - A comprehensive review of the Proposed Operation of the TRIGA-MARK II Nuclear Reactor, 1970 December 11 (Box 2)
  - Fundamental Nuclear Research, 1970 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Atomic Energy Commission on Trustees of Columbia, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    (Transcripts of court hearings, Docket no. 50-208: November 18, 19 and 20, 1969 and July 10, 1970.)